Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ל"א Lamed Aleph
31, we pick up from about eight lines from the bottom, two
dots. אמר רב, Amar Rav, כל האסורין, Kol Ha'asurin, it's also six
lines from the beginning of the widest lines. Okay, I'm sorry, well
actually the end of the previous line, כל האסורין לגבי מזבח. Kol
Ha'asurin Legabei Mizbe'ach. So the משנה Mishnah says everything forbidden to the
altar, the offspring are permissible, and then it, and that was the
first position, the first statement of that was an אתנן, Esnan, but
now the משנה Mishnah generalizes it, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer disagreed
by the child of a טריפה. Treifah. So let's take a look.
First we broaden the debate. אמר רב, Amar Rav, כל האסורין לגבי
מזבח וולדותיהן מותרין, Kol Ha'asurin Legabei Mizbe'ach Veladoteihen Mutarin, anything that is
forbidden to the altar, their children are permissible, so the children of
a רובע Rovei'a and a נרבע Nirva or a נעבד Ne'evad and
a מוקצה, Muktza, all those things. ותניא עלה, Vetanya Alah, but we
have a ברייתא Baraita on it, רבי אליעזר אוסר, Rabbi Eliezer Oser,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says forbidden. So as opposed to our משנה
Mishnah where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only disagrees by the child of
a טריפה, Treifah, we have a ברייתא Baraita that says that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer forbids the children of all forbidden animals, that their
children as well are forbidden.
אמר רב הונא בר חיננא אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Huna Bar
Chinena Amar Rav Nachman, מחלוקת כעיברו ולבסוף נרבעו. Machlokes Ke'ibru Velibasof Nirvu.
The debate is when the first animal became pregnant and then these
things were done to it that made it forbidden, right, all the
things like bestiality, worship, all those types of acts that makes the
animal forbidden.
We're not up to טריפה Treifah yet. דרבי אליעזר סבר עובר ירך
אמו, DeRabbi Eliezer Savar Ubar Yerech Imo, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
that the fetus is like a part of the mother. So if
the mother is worshipped or the mother is set aside for עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah or the mother gores or is used in an
act of bestiality, then the fetus is part of it and therefore
the fetus becomes forbidden. רבנן סברי לאו ירך אמו. Rabbanan Savri Lav
Yerech Imo. No, it's independent, so all those things happened to the
mother, not to the fetus. אבל נרבעו ולבסוף עיברו, Aval Nirvu Velibasof
Ibru, but if first they did this, this forbidden state occurred, for
example, they were used in bestiality and then they became pregnant, so
when the act was done it was not done to the fetus,
it was only done to the mother, then the mother becomes pregnant,
then the only question is does the status of the mother somehow
transfer to the fetus? In that case, דברי הכל מותרין, Divrei Hakol
Mutarin, everybody would say it's permissible. Why should it be that just
because the mother was worshipped, that status should transfer to the fetus
if the fetus came later? Okay, so that's a very logical debate.
רבא אמר, Rava Amar, רבא Rava says no, it's even a further
debate. מחלוקת כשנרבעו ולבסוף עיברו. Machlokes Keshenirvu Velibasof Ibru. They actually debate
even if first the animal was used in bestiality and then it
became pregnant. So what's the logic to say that passes on to
the fetus? דרבי אליעזר סבר זה וזה גורם אסור. DeRabbi Eliezer Savar
Zeh Vezeh Gorem Assur. This and this that caused is forbidden, meaning
that this fetus was formed through the mother and through the father.
The father presumably was not used in such acts. And nevertheless, since
this fetus was formed through the mother and the father, one of
the contributing factors was the mother that was forbidden, that forbidden status
passes on to the fetus. Now that is, right, not so obvious.
Even if in general you rule זה וזה גורם אסור, Zeh Vezeh
Gorem Assur, right,
let's take a more extreme example. Let's say both the mother and
the father were worshipped or both mother and father were used in
bestiality. There's still no proof, evidence, that why that status should pass
on to the fetus. It's not like they're forbidden in הנאה, Hana'ah,
it's just a פסול, P'sul, an invalidity to the altar. So just
because it's true about the parents, even if they were the only
cause of it being formed, even both the mother and the father,
it's not clear why we should say that should pass on. So
by saying זה וזה גורם אסור, Zeh Vezeh Gorem Assur, it's really
saying two things. Number one, the fact that the mother was the
contributing factor
is sufficient, the problem doesn't also have to come from the father.
And number two, that this is a type of a problem that
transfers on even to the offspring, which is, I would say, the
more fundamental חידוש, Chiddush, which we are not explaining where we know
that from. That is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds. רבנן סברי
זה וזה גורם מותר. Rabbanan Savri Zeh Vezeh Gorem Mutar. And the
Rabbis hold no, the mother wasn't the only cause, the father was
also the cause and therefore it's okay. So presumably even the Rabbis
would agree if it was a problem both the mother and the
father had. So therefore that's the issue. It became pregnant later and
does this problem pass on to the offspring, A in general, B
if only the mother had the problem. אבל עיברו ולבסוף נרבעו, Aval
Ibru Velibasof Nirvu, but if first it was pregnant and then it
was used in these forbidden acts, then דברי הכל אסורין, Divrei Hakol
Assurin, everybody would agree that the fetus would be forbidden, the act
would apply to the fetus as well. Why? דרבא לטעמיה, DeRava Letaimei,
רבא Rava goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבא, De'amar Rava, and
this is what we said earlier in the דף, Daf, ולד נרבעת
אסורה, Vlad Nirvat Assura, if you have a fetus that was in
the mother when the mother was used in bestiality, the fetus is
forbidden. Why? הוא וולדו נרבעו. Hu Ve'vlado Nirvu. The act of bestiality
occurred to the fetus as well. The fetus is part of the
mother, עובר ירך אמו. Ubar Yerech Imo. ולד נוגחת אסורה, Vlad Nogachas
Assur, if the fetus was in the mother when it gored, it's
forbidden. הוא וולדו ניגחו. Hu Ve'vlado Nigchu. It and its fetus gored.
So if the animal does, does the status of the mother apply
to the animal? If the animal was pregnant when it occurred, that
would be the question of עובר ירך אמו, Ubar Yerech Imo, is
it part of the mother or not? Either that is the debate
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן, Rabbanan, or according to
רבא, Rava, he's of the position that it is part of the
mother. the mother so he says everybody agrees that that case is
a problem. The other possibility is let's say it became pregnant afterwards
and there the question is does the status pass on to the
child number one in general and number two if the mother is
the only cause. לשנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, here's another way of explaining
the debate that it's go that it's not about when it became
pregnant but it's about when it became sanctified. Let's take a look.
אמרי לה, Amri lah, so here's another version of it. אמר הונא
בר חיננא אמר רב, Amar Huna bar Chinana amar Rav, אמר רב
נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, מחלוקת שנרבעו, machlokes shenirbe'u, first they became were
used in bestiality, שנרבעו כשהן מוקדשין, shenirbe'u keshen mukdashin, I'm sorry, שנרבעו
כשהן מוקדשין. shenirbe'u keshen mukdashin. They were already sanctified and then they
were used in bestiality, this animal, and then it gave birth to
an offspring. דרבי אליעזר סבר ביזוי מילתא ורבנן סברי לא. De-Rabbi Eliezer
savar bizuy milta ve-Rabbanan savri lo. So now we're dealing with a
much more if you would less fundamental more rabbinic or more aesthetic
problem. If it became invalid the mother when it was already a
sacrifice, then it's very like it's a big stigma, it's very it's
very inappropriate, you know, to be using this animal, I mean it's
אסור assur anyway, but the point is is that then it's like
then it's like פאס נישט pas nisht is what we would say,
that psh, you know, once it gets that status when it's already
a sacrifice, it's very clearly labeled as something that is completely rejected
to the altar. And in that type of a case even presumably
if it became pregnant later, we would pass that status on to
the fetus because that is a very evident problem and therefore it
would continue on to the fetus. Wonder whether it would apply to
the child of the child, I don't know, but at least it
would pass on to the child because it was already like a
really blatant problem, it was already it was already sanctified and then
this problem occurred. אבל, Aval, דרבי אליעזר סבר ביזוי מילתא ורבנן סברי
לא. de-Rabbi Eliezer savar bizuy milta ve-Rabbanan savri lo. No, it's not
such an issue. It only applies to the mother because it only
applies to the mother, it doesn't apply to the child. אבל נרבעו
כשהן חולין, Aval nirbe'u keshen chullin,
but if it occurred before they were sanctified, הואיל ואישתנו, ho'il ve-ishtannu,
since the child is something different, דברי הכל מותר, divrei hakol mutar,
everybody says it's okay. Again, not clear whether the mother was pregnant
at the time. Maybe even if the mother was pregnant, the opposite
extreme, even we wouldn't say עובר ירך אמו, uvar yerech imo, but
or but certainly if it wasn't pregnant, the fact that it became
invalid when it wasn't a sacrifice yet is not such a blatant,
you know, offensive issue and therefore we would not pass it on
to the fetus. That's how he says it. רבא אמר רב נחמן,
Rava amar Rav Nachman, Rava says in the name of Rav Nachman,
מחלוקת כשנרבעו כשהן חולין. machlokes keshenirbe'u keshen chullin. No, they're debating even
when it was not yet sanctified and it became it was used
in this act. דרבי אליעזר סבר ביזוי מילתא, De-Rabbi Eliezer savar bizuy
milta, Rabbi Eliezer says even when it's חולין, chullin, you know, these
temple invalidities are so, you know, are you know so problematic, are
so offensive, that once it gets labeled that passes on even to
the fetus, presumably even if it becomes pregnant later. ורבנן סברי הואיל
ואישתנו מותר. Ve-Rabbanan savri ho'il ve-ishtannu mutar. No, the child is a
different thing, the status of the mother does not pass on. אבל
נרבעו כשהן מוקדשין, Aval nirbe'u keshen mukdashin, but if it was the
status came when they were already sanctified, דברי הכל אסור, divrei hakol
assur, everybody agrees that that's highly offensive and that therefore the status
would pass on. So according to this, it's not an issue about
עובר ירך אמו, uvar yerech imo, it's a question about when do
we say presumably even if the mother becomes pregnant later, when do
we say the status of the mother passes on to the child?
And that is a function of, you know, almost an aesthetic issue
of how offensive it is and therefore how much would we see
it transfer to the child. But there are two questions here. If
the fetus was there at the time of the problem, it's an
issue of עובר ירך אמו, uvar yerech imo, is it part of
the mother? If it became pregnant later, then it's a question of
should we say that the status passes on to the fetus at
all? Not clear why we would say that. Here at least the
גמרא Gemara gives a reason of an idea of עובר ירך אמו.
uvar yerech imo. Okay, now let us
I'm sorry not עובר ירך אמו, uvar yerech imo, some he gives
the reason about ביזוי מילתא, bizuy milta, about being offensive. Now I
should say there's one other concept which we're going to turn to
in a minute when we get to טריפה, treifa, which is we
know when it comes to something that's really forbidden to be eaten,
we say היוצא מן הטמא טמא, ha-yotzei min ha-tamei tamei, that something
coming from a non-kosher animal is non-kosher. And that only means that
doesn't only mean that milk of a pig is non-kosher, it even
means milk of a cow if the cow is a טריפה treifa
is also non-kosher. So there we do have an idea that the
status transfers on to the to the, you know, products that come
from something, but that is specifically a הלכה halacha about כשרות. kashrus.
Is that what the גמרא Gemara is assuming here according to the
opinions that it passes on to the child, a similar concept? The
same way if it comes from a טריפה treifa animal it's טריפה,
treifa, if it comes from a animal פסול למזבח pasul le-mizbe'ach it's
also פסול למזבח? pasul le-mizbe'ach? Maybe. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara never
exactly spells out why the status of the mother should pass on
to the child and at least here at the bottom it suggested
this idea of ביזוי מילתא. bizuy milta. There were two questions.
First I was just going to ask how does he resolve all
these multiple opinions on this?
Yes, it's a question about how you know which version you פסקן
pasken and according to whom you פסקן. pasken. Right, I'm forgetting I
checked the רמב"ם Rambam yesterday but I'm forgetting exactly which way he
comes out on this, yeah. But anyways the only person פסקן pasken
in קדשים Kodashim is the רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay, yes Michael.
Someone said it's you know surprised that they haven't brought in you
know the words הקריבהו נא לפחתך. hakrivehu na le-pachatecha.
Maybe that could be what ביזוי מילתא bizuy milta means, but it's
questionable whether you would use that idea if it's an offspring. הקריבהו
נא לפחתך Hakrivehu na le-pachatecha is a phrase that the גמרא Gemara
quotes to often say like This thing is just not appropriate as
a קרבן, korban, but that usually is because it's physically, there's something
directly obvious about the thing itself that you wouldn't even give this
as a gift to an important person. Here it's the offspring of
something that has a very non-physical problem, even the mother has a
non-physical problem. So I don't think that is appropriate. ביזוי מצוה bizuy
mitzvah more has to do with our almost religious aesthetic type of
stigma? Non-physical ones? I don't know, it'd be interesting. I'd have to
check. You can do a little research, Bar-Ilan, check it out. But
I think that it's not so obvious that that principle would apply
here. Now we get onto, that's the debate of the ברייתא braita
that has them debating across the board. In the משנה mishna they
debate the issue just about the offspring of a טריפה, treifa, okay?
And now we're going to have to see, A, what's the debate
about and B, Michael's question, how is it that a טריפה treifa
had children? So let's take a look.
וטרפה, V'treifa, says, מר Mar says, למאן דאמר, leman de'amar, take out
this little troubling word אינה eina here, למאן דאמר טריפה ילדה, leman
de'amar treifa yalda, as you know in this מסכת masechet there are
a lot of text issues. Anyway, according to the opinion that a
טריפה treifa can give birth, can become pregnant and give birth, so
then it's not hard to understand the scenario. משכחת לה, Mashkachat lah,
the scenario could be כגון שנטרפה, kegon shenitrefa, first it became a
טריפה, treifa, that's possible, ולבסוף עיברה, u'levasof ibra, then it became pregnant,
because you would assume that it's possible for a טריפה treifa to
become pregnant. ובה פליגי. U'veha peligi. Okay, so that's the scenario. Now
let's understand the debate whether the offspring of a טריפה treifa is
a problem. רבי אליעזר סבר זה וזה גורם אסור, Rabbi Eliezer savar
zeh v'zeh gorem assur, we're back to זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh
gorem, that's forbidden. ורבנן סברי זה וזה גורם מותר. V'rabanan savri zeh
v'zeh gorem mutar. No, it's okay. Now here, it could be that
it's more understandable why everybody agrees that if there, if it were
the single cause it would be a problem because here it's also
a non-kosher food, as it were, a טריפה. treifa. So here the,
you might say that yes, the status should pass on to the
child. And the only reason the rabbis would say not is because
of a זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem. This fetus was not
created just by the mother, it was also created by the father.
Again, think about it, if the mother gave birth, if the mother
was a טריפה treifa maybe, although we'll continue to see some cases
in the גמרא. Gemara. Think about it, if the mother gave milk
it would be forbidden, so if the mother gives an offspring, why
isn't it forbidden? And it's independent. All right, so we're going to
get to that. But anyway, at least here you understand that in
principle the status should transfer and the rabbis have to say, no,
maybe not, זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem, maybe other things like
Michael is saying it's more independent of the mother. We'll get to
that. But anyway, then it's a simple debate of whether the status
of the mother transfers to the child, which would mean also that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say it's not just that it is
forbidden for the altar, but it's even forbidden to be eaten, presumably,
although רש"י Rashi says no, maybe they're just debating about use for
the temple. תוספות Tosafot points out that the גמרא Gemara in חולין
Chullin says that they're debating both. That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
saying it really the full status of טריפה treifa passes on, just
like the milk would be טריפה, treifa, the child is טריפה, treifa,
and you can't use it not only for the altar but even
you can't eat it. That's assuming it became pregnant later. למאן דאמר
טריפה אינה חיה Leman de'amar treifa eina chaya or אינה יולדת eina
yoledet it should be. According to the position that a טריפה treifa
cannot have children, so the scenario cannot be that first it was
a טריפה. treifa. So משכחת לה, mashkachat lah, the scenario has to
be כגון שעיברה ולבסוף נטרפה. kegon she'ibra u'levasof nitrefa. First it became
pregnant and then it became a טריפה, treifa, right? That would be
the only way it could be a טריפה treifa and give birth.
ובה פליגי, U'veha peligi, and what's the debate? רבי אליעזר סבר עובר
ירך אמו הוא. Rabbi Eliezer savar ubar yerech imo hu. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says the fetus is a thigh of the mother. So
if the mother became a טריפה, treifa, the status applies to the
fetus. ורבנן סברי עובר לאו ירך אמו הוא. V'rabanan savri ubar lav
yerech imo hu. No, it would not apply to, it's not a
part of the mother. Now this is, it should be pointed out,
not so obvious that it's similar to the idea of worshipping the
mother or using the mother in bestiality. There, an act, what was
problematic was the act that was done. It was worshipped. It was
used in bestiality. If you see the fetus as a part of
the mother, a limb of the mother, then the act was done
to the fetus as well. Here, it's not like there is an
act of becoming a טריפה treifa and we say this was done
to the animal. There's just a reality that it's טריפה, treifa, it's
got some physical problem with it. Well, the fetus doesn't have that
physical problem. And if you would say, but it's part of a
mother that does, then that should be a problem even if it
first became a טריפה treifa and then it became a fetus, because
then it's still part of a mother that's טריפה. treifa. So this
is, תוספות Tosafot points that issue out,
that even if you said עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo for
the idea of using in bestiality or worshipping, it's not at all
clear you would say it for the טריפה treifa idea because it's
not like there's an act of becoming a טריפה, treifa, the act
was done to the fetus. Okay, so here תוספות Tosafot says it's
about more the health of the animal, the fetus has
a separate entity. I mean, even if it's ירך אמו, yerech imo,
the health of the mother does not mean that it itself will
not be happy, healthy. And therefore תוספות Tosafot says it's much more
questionable if you should apply עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo here.
They do, but תוספות Tosafot just says, he points out because he's
bothered that a general position that normally does hold of it doesn't
hold of it here. So he says you don't have to apply
it, this is a real extension of that concept.
Okay, so here's going to be a problem too.
Well yes, and that's why everybody's assuming the mother is the primary
factor. The only question is that if
the father is... So right exactly. So bracketing ירך אמו Yerech Imo
which is a real extension, the more interesting question here is, you
know, or the more is whether you say that this is like
the milk of the mother, the offspring of a טריפה Treifa is
it a טריפה? Treifa? And the גמרא Gemara says that we based
that the reason to say no is זה וזה גורם, Zeh Ve-Zeh
Gorem, it's not just the mother, but as Michael indicated, there's other
reasons as well. So let's keep on reading in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר,
Modim Chachamim Le-Rabbi Eliezer, so the rabbis agreed to Rabbi Eliezer that
even if the fetus of a טריפה Treifa is not a טריפה,
Treifa, the child of a טריפה Treifa is not, they agreed באפרוח
ביצת טריפה, Be-Efroach Beitzas Treifa, let's say of a chick coming from
an egg of a chicken that was a טריפה, Treifa, okay, so
it's similar to the offspring, but it wasn't born live, it was
born as an egg, they would agree that in that case שאסור,
She-Assur, that it is forbidden. Right now by the way, if you
just had a if you just had a not a chick, but
you just had eggs from a chicken that was טריפה, Treifa, those
eggs are טריפה, Treifa, like milk from a cow that's a טריפה.
Treifa. So now we're getting to the idea that, you know, everybody
does agree that the food byproducts of טריפה Treifa animals are טריפה.
Treifa. So why exactly is the child, the calf, different? And here
it's going to clarify that by talking about a middle case where
if it started as an egg, that would have been טריפה, Treifa,
but now it's a chick, and this says you know what, the
rabbis agree that that is forbidden. How is that different? So let's
see how it explains why that's different.
מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason?
עד כאן לא פליגי עליה דרבי אליעזר Ad Kan Lo Pligi Alei
De-Rabbi Eliezer אלא בולד בהמה, Ela Be-Valad Behema, they only disagree with
Rabbi Eliezer and say that this the child does not become a
טריפה Treifa when you're talking about the offspring of like a, you
know, of a of a of a mammal, as it were, of
a live birth. Why? דמאוירא קא רבייא, De-Me-Avira Ka Ravya, it grows
from the air. I'll explain this in a minute. אבל ביצת טריפה,
Aval Beitzas Treifa, but the or the chick from the egg of
a טריפה, Treifa, מגופא דתרנגולת קא רבייא, Mi-Gufa De-Tarnigoles Ka Ravya, that
comes from the actual body of the chicken itself, of the hen
itself, אפילו רבנן מודי, Afilu Rabbanan Modi, even the rabbis agree. Now
what's the difference air versus body? So רש"י Rashi says two explanations,
one during gestation and one after birth. The gestation one makes a
little more sense to me at least. He says that when a
egg is growing in a in a hen's, you know, body, it's
like very much, you know, part of like this whole, you know,
like embedded within the, you know, physical body of the of the
chick of the chicken, of the hen. And therefore it's very much
considered completely just a piece of the hen. And therefore when it's
born, it completely would just be a hen and if it transforms
later into a chick, but fine, nobody's going to say that it
is not like a piece of a טריפה Treifa animal. But he
says when a fetus grows, you know, there's air in the sense
that it's in the womb, and it's yes, I know it's not
air, I know that there's liquid there, but the point is it's
not as physically intertwined, you know, in the body, it's more retains
a certain independence. So
even if you say הלכתית Halachically it's part of the mother, all
along, you know, the whole fact that there's a debate of ירך
אמו Yerech Imo or not means that it it retains a there
is a certain independence of it. So therefore when it's born, we
don't consider it as much just a piece of the mother, and
therefore we're able to say that if it's a separate live thing,
it's not milk. Milk is a piece of the mother. It's a
separate live thing, therefore it has independence at least when it's born,
and the status of the mother doesn't factor. As opposed to an
egg is always seen much more as a piece of the mother
and when it's laid it's a piece of the mother and therefore
the status remains. Now part one minute, that's the you can all
tell me your problems in a second.
That's the difference during gestation. Okay, but there's also the difference when
it actually grows. Now here I would have said when it's born.
Now here I would have said actually the reverse of what רש"י
Rashi said, what I've been hinting to, that when the when the
egg is first laid, it's not an independent entity, it's just like
a food that was born. So even if later it develops into
a chick, right, it was all just sort of seen as like
a food byproduct of the mother, whereas when a live birth, it's
automatically seen as more independent. That's what you said. That's what I
would say. רש"י Rashi says no, רש"י Rashi says the following. He
says that when live animals are born, they grow an enormous amount
after they're born, right, from the time a calf is born till
it becomes a cow. Whereas chicks, you know, the difference between a
chick and a bird, the size is not so huge. Now it's
all relative, I know. So that's why I didn't really understand that.
So רש"י Rashi says since there's more independent growth or more a
greater growth after it's born by the live births, that shows that
they're more independent. Whereas things that are born more more closer to
being completed, you know, those things are not are less are more
part of their mothers. But I don't get that so much. I
would have said the opposite. By the way, when it exits the
mother, the egg is much less independent, you know, than the calf,
which is why I like the first explanation. Now we'll hear everybody's
problems. Yes.
Yeah, if anything a skin... there around because the
placenta's intertwined with the mother's blood vessels right up until the egg
is
a shell and it's and it's eventually gets a shell.
Yeah.
But doesn't the egg physically, meaning the fetus is in this embryonic
sac with this fluid, it has some independence? When the egg is
growing, isn't it like just tightly within a cluster within the inside
of the mother's body?
No, less than the amniotic sac is.
Wait, there's no like fluid that gives it some independence, right? Isn't
it like just all
intertwined? Oh, you're saying the egg itself, if you make the analogy,
the egg, the fetus is has independence within the egg from all
of the stuff that surrounds it.
I would have said the opposite for the first explanation.
Right. The second one I don't even begin to understand. Right, no,
no, yeah, it's internal. All right, so I don't know what to
say. Never seen two explanations for a פרשה. parsha. Well, the גמרא's
Gemara going to continue to give an explanation. Look, if you like
pick my explanation, although I don't know if it fits in the
words of the גמרא, Gemara, but I would say, like I said,
when the egg is born, it's just like a food byproduct, it's
not yet an animal. So that follows the more normal rule that
the byproducts of the mother of a טריפה treifa animal apply to
the child, whereas when the animal is born, it's independent and therefore
it's not just a product of the mother.
And it would certainly be the case today because eggs from chickens
are not fertilized.
Right. Right. Well, that no, but we're only talking about the chick.
An egg everybody agrees is טריפה. treifa. Only question is when it's
a when it's an animal that comes from the mother, does do
we give that independent or do the רמב״ם Rambam says something like
that. The רמב״ם Rambam emphasizes food that comes from a טריפה treifa
animal is טריפה. treifa. So that's sort of the emphasis of the
רמב״ם. Rambam. That's just הלכה היוצא מן הטמא halacha hayotzei min hatamei
as opposed to when it's like a animal that comes from an
animal. Okay, so here anyway it started much more as food. And
animal also, right? I understand, but not immediately. And here though when
it started as an egg, it started much more as food. That's
how I would like to say it. Let's keep on going. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבא לרב הונא. Amar lei
Rava le-Rav Huna. So רבא Rava said to רב הונא, Rav Huna,
who said that they did not that there are that they debate
in some they agree in some cases that it would be a
problem. תני דמסייע לך. Tani de-mesayei lach. I'll bring a ברייתא braita
that supports you, or actually a משנה mishna I should say that
supports you. מלא תרווד רימה הבא מאדם חי. Malei tarvad rima haba
me-adam chai. A filled sort of a ladle of of
maggots that come from a live person. I must first must have
leprosy or something. I don't know how a person has maggots growing
in his skin.
Doctors see these cases in their medical.
Is it is it leprosy or?
No, it's just infection.
Infections and the skin is rotting and dying.
Yeah, it's pretty horrible, but please describe some for me.
So the question is if they're sort of rotting and growing in
the skin, do they become considered part of the skin? So there's
some very loose analogy to what degree something is part of something
else. So, but it's going to be a similar debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, רבי אליעזר מטמא. Rabbi
Eliezer metamei. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says they're like part of the
skin and therefore when they fall off they're like limbs of a
dead person or certainly when the person dies they're considered part of
the dead person. וחכמים מטהרים. Ve-Chachamim metaharim. The חכמים Chachamim say that
it's no, it's not the person's skin, it's not a problem. עד
כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר. Ad kan lo pligi rabanan
alei de-Rabbi Eliezer. So the whole debate is אלא ברימה ella birima
by these maggots דפירשא בעלמא הוא de-pirsha be-alma hu that that's only
like waste, meaning it's not obviously not really the skin itself. So
there the rabbis are willing to say I don't consider it part
of the person.
אבל ביצה, Aval beitza, what a what a you know huge jump,
that's by maggots from skin, אבל ביצה דמגופה דתרנגולת הוא אפילו רבנן
מודו. aval beitza de-migufeh de-tarnagolta hu afilu rabanan modu. But something that
would much more be part of the thing itself, like a chick
from a mother, then from a hen, that should you know or
certainly the egg that started as the egg from the hen, that
they should agree should be part of the body. Now again, if
all it's saying is that a hen that lays an egg, the
egg is more seen as a you know connected to the mother
than when it gives birth to a live animal, fine, you could
say that, you said that already. How exactly that idea is supported
by this idea of the maggots is not so clear. But again
it says well the only time we see the rabbis debate are
in extreme cases,
maggots, live birth, anything less extreme like an egg, that presumably they
would agree. So the גמרא Gemara says back to him, אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye says back, אדרבה, Adaraba, no, איפכא
מסתברא, ipcha mistabra, we could say the opposite. עד כאן לא פליג
רבי אליעזר דרבנן, Ad kan lo plig Rabbi Eliezer de-rabanan, the opposite,
maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only says that it's part of the
person only by
maggots, why? דאיקרי אדם מחיים רימה de-ikrei adam me-chayim rima because even
human beings when they're alive are still called maggots. דכתיב, De-chtiv, very
uplifting גמרא, Gemara, בתקוות אנוש רימה, be-tikvat enosh rima, the whole hope
you know of humans is maggots, you're all going to become maggots
eventually. ובן אדם תולעה, U-ven adam toleia, and human beings into worms.
So from the very beginning we see ourselves as maggots to be.
אבל, Aval, that's why he says it, אבל ביצה, aval beitza, when
it comes to an egg,
אימת גדלה, eimat gadla, and now we're going to explain why egg
has greater independence, when does the chick grow from the egg? Maybe
yes, the egg is the byproduct and if it were just an
egg everybody would agree that eggs from a טריפה treifa is טריפה.
treifa. But when does the chick grow?
כי גדלה Ki gadla וכי מסרכא vechi masrecha when it's spoiling, עפרא
בעלמא הוא afra b'alma hu it's dust, meaning the way I would
interpret this, okay, it seems to be saying like that that it's
laid as an egg, it's a problem, it's a byproduct of a
טריפה treifah thing. But then the growing of the chick occurs after
it's laid, and therefore the chick of the egg is independent of
the mother. The egg as an egg, if you would eat it
then, that would be טריפה, treifah, but the chick is growing independent
of the mother, it's a new development and therefore it's not given
the mother's status. Okay, so he says, and that by the way
is the הלכה halacha is that whether it is the live birth
of an animal or whether it is a chick that grows from
a טריפה treifah animal, they are not טריפה treifah even if the
mother is טריפה, treifah, but the eggs of a טריפה treifah chicken
and the milk of a טריפה treifah cow are. Okay, so the
milk of a טריפה treifah cow, the eggs of a טריפה treifah
chicken are טריפה, treifah, okay, but when if a טריפה treifah cow
gives birth to a calf or if a chicken gives birth to
a fertilized egg and it grows into a chick, the calf and
the chick are okay. They are independent of the mother. And again,
the logic a little more is that the egg would since it
came from a טריפה treifah food, but here we are saying no,
its growth is different from its being as an egg. And that
happens as a second stage and that is not given the mother's
status.
Anytime you eat it as an egg, it's a problem. Whether it's
fertilized or not?
No, if it's fertilized it's a problem, but if it's after it
became a chick, it's not a problem.
No, no, I said anytime you eat it as an egg, yes.
Correct. Correct. ועוד, ve'od, let me just finish this thought, ועוד תניא
בהדיא, ve'od tanya behedya, we say it explicitly, מודה רבי אליעזר לחכמים
באפרוח ביצת טריפה שמותר. modeh Rabbi Eliezer lachachamim be'efroach beitzat treifah shemutar.
Look, we have a ברייתא braita that says Rabbi Eliezer agrees, even
though he says that the calf, now that's even the reverse, the
calf has more of the status of a mother, that's what you
wanted to say, that even though he says the calf is a
טריפה, treifah, that's because it's born directly from the mother, but the
chick that comes later, and he would even say that that even
better than the calf, the opposite of what you were saying. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said back, כי תניא תניא, ki tanya
tanya, look, if you've got a ברייתא, braita, you've got a ברייתא.
braita. I can't say anything. You say like logically I would have
said that the egg is that the chick is worse, but he
says but actually my logic tells me that the chick is better,
we have a ברייתא braita that says that. So Rabbi Eliezer only
said the calf of a טריפה treifah is a טריפה, treifah, but
the chick of a טריפה treifah hen is okay. That growth occurs
after it's born, it's more independent of the mother. Yes.
Isn't that because the nutrition is coming from and how does that
affect the product? Because even if it's an egg, that nutrition is
coming from the mother, that the chick is eating the nutrition.
Well, yes, but not but not sort of in an active way,
meaning it originally originated in the mother, but now it's coming but
now it's happening outside of the mother.
Right, and I think that's why in the end the גמרא Gemara
is willing to say that the case of the egg is even
better, because yes, it all originated in the mother, but in the
end that's occurring outside of the mother. And therefore as it's growing
and as it's developing into a chick, it's not
I understand it originated in the mother.
No, because I mean if the mother passes something on that's negative
to the fetus.
Oh, that we're going to get to. Okay, we're going to get
to that in a minute. Okay, that's the next part of the
משנה. mishna. I know, no. I understand what you're saying, but the
answer is that exactly what we're about to get to next in
the גמרא. Gemara.
And Abaye just won an argument with Rava?
He does every now and then.
Okay, anyway, but only he only conceded because of the because there
was a ברייתא. braita. What can I do? You got a ברייתא.
braita. Okay, now, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר וכו'. Rabbi Chanina ben
Antignos omer vechu'. Now we are dealing with what David said. The
משנה mishna says that Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos says if you have
a calf that is nursing from a mother and the mother is
a טריפה, treifah, you know, again has this injury or whatever, then
the calf is forbidden. So he basically seems to say that an
animal that grew and was, you know, gained its nutrition from non-kosher
products is not kosher.
But of course, פסולה מעל גבי המזבח.
psulah me'al
gabi hamizbeach. What? פסולה מעל גבי
המזבח.
psulah me'al gabi
hamizbeach. I'm sorry, you are correct. You're correct. פסולה מעל גבי המזבח,
psulah me'al gabi hamizbeach, that is correct. So he's not saying that
it's not kosher, but at least to say that that's enough to
stigmatize it for קרבן. korban. Okay, so that again is very strange,
right? Where did we have this idea? It was hard we were
struggling enough with the idea why does the status of the mother
pass to the fetus or its child just in terms of קרבן
korban purposes, but here he's actually just saying that the fact of
a problematic food gives it a problematic status. That to the גמרא
Gemara seems a little bit too much. So let's take right, right,
right. Let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the reasoning? אילימא דמפטמה מינה, eilima demifatma mineh, which
is what we would have thought, it was fattened by this non-kosher
food and that gives it a an invalid status. אלא מעתה הכילא
כרשיני עבודה זרה, ela me'ata hechila karshinei avodah zarah, so if you
say that, then if you were to let's say have fed it
grain from that was that was, you know, used for for idol
worship or for offerings to an idol, הכא נמי דאסירא, hacha nami
de'asira, would you say that that's also forbidden? So the answer is
yes, why not? So the answer is as רש"י Rashi says, because
the גמרא Gemara before said the example of מוקצה לעבודה זרה muktzeh
l'avodah zarah is you handed... this animal over to the priests and
they were feeding it these כרשינין, karshinin, but that's only because it's
מוקצה, muktzah, that's only because it was handed over and was designated
for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, just being fed by this grain of
עבודה זרה avoda zara does not make the animal forbidden. So how
could he say what?
Am I actually allowed to do that? But just if I did.
No, right, exactly. So אלא תני רב חנינא ella tani Rav Chanina
or the animal did it by itself, whatever. אלא תני רב חנינא.
ella tani Rav Chanina. So obviously just what it was fed by
is not enough to invalidate. אלא תני רב חנינא טריטאה ella tani
Rav Chanina Terita'ah קמיה דרבי יוחנן. kammei d'Rabbi Yochanan. So רב חנינא
טריטאה, Rav Chanina Terita'ah, unusual name but we had it before, taught
in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. כגון, kegon, it's an extreme
case, שהניקה חלב רותח משחרית לשחרית. she'henika chalav rote'ach mishacharit l'shacharit. It
ate bubbling milk, bubbling means like fresh milk, it nursed milk straight
from its mother every single morning, first thing in the morning, from
its טריפה treifa mother. הוא ויכול לעמוד עליו מעת לעת. hu v'yachol
la'amod alav me'et l'et. And that if it gets milk first thing
in the morning, then it could even if it eats more in
the day, that initial breakfast could have helped, you know, lasted for
it the whole day. Right, that's the most important meal of the
day. So therefore what it's saying is, is that it's not just
that it was got it had some non-kosher food, but that its
entire growth, as you were saying, was due to the non-kosher milk.
Every single breakfast was this non-kosher milk, that would have sufficed for
it, so we basically say the entire thing was a product, the
entire way that it grew and was, you know, and was sustained
was through this non-kosher. For him that's enough to label it as
not good for the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Again, not non-kosher, but not good
for the מזבח mizbe'ach and only in this extreme case where all
of its nutrition came from this source. Okay, so that's that position,
an extreme position which the גמרא Gemara limits somewhat. Last point, a
little bit a little not directly about this idea of what we
were saying, but obviously connected. If an animal became טריפה treifa after
it was a קרבן korban you cannot redeem it, even if it
had a מום, mum, why not? Because then there's nothing you can
do for it for you to benefit from it. You could only
feed it to your dog, or some said you could feed it
to a נכרי, nochri, but it's not acceptable, you cannot redeem a
קרבן korban unless you a ישראל Yisrael is going to benefit from
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכל הקדשים שנטרפו v'chol hakodashim shenitrefu
you can't redeem them. מנא הני מילי, mena hanei milei, where do
we know this from? דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabanan, תזבח. tizbach. This is
what it says you do by an animal that got a blemish
that you redeem. It says you may slaughter and eat it. So
the דרשה drasha is תזבח, tizbach, slaughter it, ולא גיזה, v'lo giza,
you can't shear it. That's as we know, redeemed animal is not
to be sheared. You have to slaughter and eat it. ואכלת, v'achalta,
you should eat it, you should eat it, excuse me, ולא לכלבך,
v'lo l'chalbecha, and not for your dogs, you. בשר, basar, you should
eat the meat, ולא חלב, v'lo chalav, you cannot drink you cannot
milk it and use the milk. So basically the תורה Torah is
saying if you redeemed an animal that was a קרבן, korban, the
only thing you can do is use its meat and the emphasis
of you,
ואכלת, v'achalta, means therefore only you, only a Jew, and not a
dog or no other person. Okay, מכאן שאין פודים את הקדשים להאכילן
לכלבים, mikan she'ein podin et hakodashim l'ha'achilan l'chlavim, you cannot redeem a
קרבן korban if the only thing you can do is feed it
to dogs because that is not a legitimate use. איכא דאמרי, ika
d'amri, but there are those that disagree and say you're allowed to
do it. תזבח ואכלת, tizbach v'achalta, that what do we learn from
you shall slaughter and eat? אין לך בהן היתר אלא משעת זביחה
ואילך. ein lecha bahen heter ella mish'at zvicha v'eilach. It says you
can't use it until you slaughter, you can't milk it, you can't
shear it, but once you slaughter it you can use the meat
for any purpose you want. קסבר פודים את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. kasavar
podin et hakodashim l'ha'achilan l'chlavim. Yes, you can redeem it, you can
use the meat and feed it to your dogs and therefore that
would disagree with our משנה. mishna. So the idea although this sounds
like this is an appropriateness issue, like it's not appropriate to redeem
a קרבן korban just for the sake of making dog food out
of it, that's not really the point. Really the point is whether
you have a היתר אכילה, heter achila, what the תורה Torah allows
you to do with a redeemed קרבן. korban. Okay, it only allows
you to use the meat and the question is to use the
meat for yourself, for a Jew to consume, or even for other
purposes. And if you can't use it for other purposes, then therefore
you can't redeem it. Yes.
I've brought this up before when we had the משנה, mishna, it
doesn't even talk about the possibility of giving the meat to a
נכרי. nochri.
I know, that's why I kept on inserting that into what I
was saying. I know, but but it's the same point, it's you
should eat it, right, yes.
So you said that the calf absorbed from a טריפה treifa is
okay? Right, but the milk is not. But so am I allowed
to have this calf suckle from a mother who's a טריפה? treifa?
Is that איסור הנאה? issur hana'ah? No, no, no, no. First of
all, it's not איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, טריפה treifa is only אסור
באכילה, assur b'achila, it's not אסור בהנאה.
assur b'hana'ah. Right, I know, I understand, but you're saying you're not
supposed to be able I'm not allowed to drink the milk.
Not allowed to drink it, you're allowed to get הנאה hana'ah from
it.
I'm allowed to get okay.
Okay, so there's the only question is, as פסח Pesach is coming
up, you know, and I I don't know if they do this
here, but when I was growing up everybody was very מחמיר machmir
to make sure that they buy milk and eggs before פסח, Pesach,
right, because the cow maybe is eating grain on פסח Pesach and
then is the milk and eggs that grow from it. So anyway,
רב משה Rav Moshe basically says that's nonsense, but anyway we like
to be מחמיר machmir for it anyway. But that is a case
where it's איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, right, that the thing that it's
eating is אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, the the חמץ, chametz, and is
the thing that became a byproduct of the calf that got a
little bit fed by this, is that considered somehow like there's a
הנאה hana'ah problem indirectly you got הנאה hana'ah from the חמץ. chametz.
But even those whole discussions which רב משה Rav Moshe completely rejects
except maybe in a... עבודה זרה avodah zarah cases, is only by
הנאה. hana'ah. When it's a case like this, it's טרייף traif milk,
but not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, then the only issue you get
is this one idea that that if it had it every single
morning and it's a problem for מזבח, mizbe'ach, but it's certainly not
a הנאה hana'ah problem, it's certainly not a problem for non-מזבח mizbe'ach
purposes.
Thank you for that, Cade. Anyway, so the other, but just to
repeat, the other major issue is, is the offspring of the mother
like it for פסולי המזבח? psulei hamizbe'ach? If the mother was pregnant
when the problem happened, that's the problem of עובר ירך אמו, ubar
yerech imo, although טריפה treifa is a question if you call it
an event, but then it's the issue of עובר ירך אמו. ubar
yerech imo. If the mother got pregnant afterwards, then it's a more
fundamental question of why should we ever say the status of the
mother passes down to the child at all? זה וזה גורם, zeh
v'zeh gorem, or even without זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem, why
should the status pass down? That's maybe more of an issue by
טריפה treifa where we know the status transfers when it comes to
the issue of non-כשר kosher food. And there the גמרא Gemara made
a difference, said, yeah, by food clearly if it's an egg or
milk, but by a live offspring, that's a different, that's a question
about whether the status passes down. Okay, so הדרן עלך כל האסורין.
hadran alach kol ha'assurin. That was quite a fascinating פרק perek about
things that are אסור assur to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And now we
move into the end game here, right, the יש בקדשי מזבח, yesh
bekodshei mizbe'ach, which is a nice little wrap-up of ways in which
קרבנות korbanot are different than things that are sanctified for בדק הבית.
bedek habayit. And this also has a obviously a direct tie-in to
תמורה, tmurah, because תמורה tmurah is all about קרבנות, korbanot, not about
קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei bedek habayit. Let's take a look at the
next פרק. perek. יש
בקדשי מזבח שאין בקדשי בדק הבית. yesh bekodshei mizbe'ach she'ein bekodshei bedek
habayit. There are aspects that apply to things that are sanctified for
קרבנות korbanot that do not apply to things that are sanctified for
the temple treasury. ויש בקדשי בדק הבית שאין בקדשי מזבח. veyesh bekodshei
bedek habayit she'ein bekodshei mizbe'ach. And there's the reverse, special laws that
apply to things that are for temple treasury that don't apply to
קרבנות. korbanot. Now we're going to list them.
קדשי מזבח עושים תמורה. kodshei mizbe'ach osim tmurah. Things that are sacrificed
can make a תמורה. tmurah. And there's a question about whether we
have the next גרסא, girsa, so let's read the parentheses. וקדשי בדק
הבית אין עושים תמורה. vekodshei bedek habayit ein osim tmurah. You don't
do that by things sanctified for the treasury. That we've been saying
all along in this פרק, perek, right? It's only about sanctified as
a קרבן. korban. קדשי מזבח חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא. kodshei
mizbe'ach chayavin aleihem mishum pigul notar vetamei. Things that were sanctified as
a קרבן, korban, as they were then brought as a קרבן, korban,
you could have the ideas of פיגול, pigul, having it, you know,
planning to eat it at the wrong time, wrong place, then it
becomes אסור assur to eat it בכרת, bekaret, or נותר, notar, it
was leftover, or טמא, tamei, it became טמא. tamei. All these things
create, create, you know, prohibition to eat it when these occur to
the meat of a קרבן. korban. That doesn't apply if it's just
sanctified. You might have other problems like מעילה, me'ilah, which we'll get
to, misuse of הקדש, hekdesh, but you don't have the concepts of
פיגול נותר וטמא. pigul notar vetamei. That's only by קרבנות. korbanot. Number
number number two. ולדן וחלבן אסור לאחר פדיונן. vladan vechalavan assur le'achar
pidyonan.
Even after you redeem a קרבן, korban, it got a בעל מום,
ba'al mum, some of the status remains, right? This has been an
ongoing theme. When you redeem something sanctified for the temple treasury, the
whole idea was for the, it was all about just value and
ownership. They sell it, it completely loses its status, it transfers to
the money. Here though, it was more of an intrinsic identity. So
A, you have to wait for a בעל מום. ba'al mum. You
could have made that point. By קרבנות korbanot you have to wait
for a בעל מום. ba'al mum. By מזבח mizbe'ach you can redeem
them right away. And even when it has a בעל מום ba'al
mum and you've redeemed it, some of the status still remains. You
cannot shear it, you cannot work
it, you cannot benefit from its milk like we just said. So
ולדן וחלבן אסור. vladan vechalavan assur. Their milk is forbidden. Even their
offspring is אסור. assur. Though the offspring is a little more complicated,
because if they actually became pregnant after they were redeemed, the offspring
is okay. The case of the offspring is that they were pregnant
before they were redeemed and gave birth after. In that case, some
of the status adheres to the offspring as well. All of that
is by קרבנות, korbanot, and it's completely irrelevant by בדק הבית, bedek
habayit, because there the קדושה kedusha is completely removed.
So what do you do with it? It's a...
alright, we'll worry about it. והשוחטן בחוץ חייב. vehashochtan bachutz chayav. And
if you slaughtered them, if it, forget that you've redeemed it, if
it hasn't been redeemed, you slaughter a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that's חייב, chayav, that's the איסור כרת issur karet
of שחיטת קדשים shechitat kodshim outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Doesn't
apply if the animal was only temple treasury. אין נותנים מהם לאומנין
בשכרן. ein notnim mehem le'umanin bischaran. And let's say you had an
animal sanctified as a קרבן, korban, you can't use it for other
purposes. You can't use it, for example, to buy a beam for
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. You can't use it to pay the
workers in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. That's pretty obvious. Those are
all the limits of the sanctified for a קרבן. korban. מה שאין
כן בקדשי בדק הבית. ma she'ein ken bekodshei bedek habayit. None of
this applies, as I've been saying. When you redeem it, it's completely
de-sanctified. There's no idea of שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, it wasn't supposed
to be brought as a קרבן. korban. There's no idea of נותר,
notar, טמא, tamei, those are ideas of קרבנות. korbanot. And you can
use money given over to the temple to pay your workers, to
pay your temple workers. Okay, now that's part of the main purpose.
Now, יש בקדשי בדק הבית. yesh bekodshei bedek habayit. Now here are
some unique things about קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei bedek habayit.
שסתם הקדשות לבדק הבית. shestam hekdeshot lebedek habayit. If somebody just says,
"I'm sanctifying this," we assume it means for the temple treasury. Even
an animal? Okay, well, we'll discuss. Presumably even an animal, and the
גמרא Gemara will... If you just don't specify, you just say sanctifying,
sanctifying means temple treasury, okay? Not קרבן. korban. הקדש בדק הבית Hekdesh
bedek habayis חל על הכל. chal al hakol. Number two, the sanctifying
things for the treasury applies to everything, whereas when you sanctify it
for a קרבן, korban, it's only for animals, okay? And kosher, unblemished,
and so on. Okay, ומועלין בגידוליהן, u'mo'alin b'giduleihen, even if they have
like things that are products of them, you sanctify a tree and
then there are fruit, and then there are we'll talk about in
the גמרא, Gemara, the prohibition of מעילה me'ilah applies not only to
the thing itself, but even to byproducts of the thing. We'll talk
in the גמרא Gemara how this is different than a קרבן. korban.
ואין בהן הנאה לבעלים, V'ein bahen hana'ah l'ba'alim, and the owners or
some say לכהנים, l'kohanim,
nobody gets benefit from them, not the owners, not the כהנים, kohanim,
just the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. As opposed to a קרבן, korban,
some קרבנות korbanos I eat, a lot of קרבנות korbanos כהנים kohanim
eat, here the idea is it is all to the temple treasury.
Yes.
I feel like we've learned all these things before.
Yes, but you know, it's an idea to pull it all together
and to make and to bring it all together. Also, part, sometimes,
you know, there's a question the academics have that some of these
nice little comprehensive things, אין בזה אלא בזה, ein b'zeh ela b'zeh,
אין בין זה לזה, ein beyn zeh l'zeh, you know, that those
might have been some of the earliest collections of the משניות Mishnayos
before that they were then sort of like parceled out and developed
more independently. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. וכלל
הוא
דכל קדשי מזבח עושין תמורה? V'khlal hu d'kol kodshei mizbe'ach osin temurah?
Is this really a rule that anything sanctified for a קרבן korban
makes תמורה? temurah? There are a lot of exceptions. הרי עופות, Harei
ofos, how about birds? דקדשי מזבח הן, D'kodshei mizbe'ach hein, that they
are קדשי מזבח, kodshei mizbe'ach, ותנן, u'tnan, we learned earlier, everybody will
remember, המנחות והעופות אין עושין תמורה. haminchos v'ha'ofos ein osin temurah. You
can't do it by
מנחות minchos and by birds. Why? They're also קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbe'ach
because it says בהמה בבהמה. behemah b'vehemah. It's only by בהמה, behemah,
not by birds, not by מנחות. minchos. So you see, there are
things that are sanctified for the altar that can't make a תמורה.
temurah. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, כי תניא אבהמה. ki tanyah
ab'hemah. When we're talking about, we're talking about בהמות behemos sanctified for
the altar. גמרא Gemara says, okay, still not a rule there. הרי
ולד קדשי מזבח הוא? Harei vlad kodshei mizbe'ach hu? How about the
child of a קרבן? korban? Right? That that's a derivative קדושה, kedushah,
but that is has sanctity of the altar. ותנן אין הולד עושה
תמורה. U'tnan ein havlad osin temurah. If something is an offspring of
a קרבן, korban, yes it's brought as a קרבן korban but it
can't make a תמורה temurah because its קדושה kedushah is only derivative,
so it doesn't apply. So the גמרא Gemara says, המני רבי יהודה
היא דאמר ולד עושה תמורה. hamani Rabbi Yehuda hi d'amar vlad osin
temurah. All right, we're going through רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says
an offspring of a קרבן korban can do a תמורה. temurah. גמרא
Gemara says, okay, but there's still exceptions. הרי תמורה עצמה, Harei temurah
atzmah, how about the תמורה temurah itself? דקדשי מזבח, D'kodshei mizbe'ach, that's
something that would be brought as a קרבן. korban. ותנן אין תמורה
עושה תמורה. U'tnan ein temurah osah temurah. Everybody agrees a תמורה temurah
can't make a תמורה, temurah, that that's derivative קדושה kedushah and can't
make a תמורה. temurah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, no, כי
תניא אעיקר זבחה. ki tanyah a'ikar zivchah. All right, fine. We're not
talking about every single thing that's a קרבן korban can make a
תמורה. temurah. We mean things that are primary, classic, paradigmatic קרבנות korbanos
make a תמורה. temurah. Okay, so not so and therefore we're not
talking about derivatives, we're not talking about תמורה, temurah, we're not talking
about ולד, vlad, we're talking about the first thing you sanctify. השתא
דאתית להכי, Hasha d'asis l'hachi, now that you're saying that, אפילו תימא
רבנן, afilu teima rabbanan, even the rabbis that say a ולד vlad
doesn't make a תמורה, temurah, כי תניא אעיקר זבחה. ki tanyah a'ikar
zivchah. We're talking about the first thing you sanctify, not some derivative
קדושה. kedushah. When it's about original קדושה kedushah for מזבח, mizbe'ach, that
always does a תמורה, temurah, as long as you're talking about בהמות
behemos and not birds. All right, now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
I wonder if this is the גמרא Gemara citing a משנה Mishnah
that's kind of a mnemonic for
for categorizing, memorizing it. Right.
Yeah, that's what you and I might say. I'm not sure the
גמרא Gemara is saying it because the גמרא Gemara never went back
to
its first answer about that מנחה minchah and birds, you know, it
only sort of said, oh now we can deal with the answer
about ולד. vlad. You know, we would have said, yeah, no problem,
מנחה, minchah, birds, whatever, it's just like a nice, you know, distillation,
it's not completely, but I don't think the גמרא Gemara is going
that far. But we might say it. All right, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. ואין מהם לאומנים, V'ein me'ham l'umanim, you can't
pay your your temple workers. הקדש בדק הבית נותנים. Hekdesh bedek habayis
nosnim. Ah, but if it were sanctified for the temple treasury, you
can use it to pay your workers. How do you know that?
אמר רב אבו אמר קרא, Amar Rav Avu amar Kra, the verse
says, ועשו לי מקדש, v'asu li mikdash, לי משלי. li misheli. When
it comes to making the temple, you can use my funds to
pay people to make the temple. Now תוספות Tosafos says, of course,
why else are you sanctifying it to the temple? So תוספות Tosafos
says, no, I would have thought that maybe if you sanctify it
to the temple, the thing itself has to be used, or maybe
if it could be sold as proceeds, but it ultimately have to
go into something that is built into the temple. Whereas when you
pay when you pay right, but right, but right, or you buy
something else, but when you pay somebody's, you know, fees or somebody's,
you know, what labor, so there's not a there's not a thing
that is now belonging to the temple, that is part of the
temple anymore. Maybe that would have to be special donations that weren't
sanctified, like you would have collections for people that wanted to pay
for, you know, the cost of labor, but maybe you could would
not be able to use sanctified funds for that. And also logically,
right, where does the sanctity go? If I have a thousand dollars
here that were sanctified and I pay the laborers, where did the
sanctity disappear? appear to? If I buy a beam that I'm going
to build in, the sanctity transfers to the beam. So where did
the sanctity go? So somehow it transfers to the abstract work that
was done? So it's not so clear you could have used the
money to pay for labor. Maybe only for objects and that we
learned that no, you can even use that money to pay for
labor. Okay. יש בקדשי בדק הבית. Yesh bekadshei bedek habayit. Now, now
we're onto things that are for the Temple treasury and the first
main thing is, we indirectly said it before, the first main thing
is is that a סתם הקדש stam hekdesh applies to the treasury
and presumably that means even of an animal. We interpret it to
be for the Temple treasury. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר מר, Amar mar, סתם הקדש לבדק הבית, stam hekdesh
lebedek habayit, an unspecified sanctity goes to the treasury, וחל על הכל,
vechal al hakol, it applies to everything. So first we're going to
focus on the that it goes to the treasury unspecified. מאן תנא?
Man tanna? Who is this תנא? tanna? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, דלא
כרבי יהושע. delo keRabbi Yehoshua. It's not Rabbi Yehoshua. He would say
that it becomes a קרבן korban if it's not specified, if it's
an animal. דתניא, Detanya, or just actually דתנן, detnan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, we also had this before.
המקדיש נכסיו, Hamakdish nechasav, you sanctify all your property, והיו בהן בהמה
vehayu bahen behemah ראויה לגבי מזבח, reuyah legabei mizbe'ach, amongst your property
was animals that could have been קרבנות, korbanot, nice cows and sheep
that were unblemished,
זכרים ונקבות, zecharim unekevot, males and females. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, Rabbi Eliezer says it all goes to the Temple treasury. It's
not a קרבן. korban. סתם הקדש Stam hekdesh is treasury. So that's
actually who our משנה Mishnah is. Let's take a look at how
he says this. זכרים ימכרו לצורכי עולות, Zecharim yimachru letzorchei olot, sell
the male animals to people that have to buy
an עולה, olah, ונקבות ימכרו לצורכי שלמים, unekevot yimachru letzorchei shelamim, sell
the females to people that have to bring שלמים, shelamim, ודמיהן, udemaihen,
but what do you do with the money? You don't use the
money for קרבנות. korbanot. No. יפלו עם שאר נכסיו לבדק הבית. Yippelu
im she'ar nechasav lebedek habayit. They go to the Temple treasury. So
it all goes to the Temple treasury. So then why are you
selling them to people that need to bring קרבנות? korbanot? That's another
idea. We even if it goes to the treasury, we agree to
the principle that if something is fit for קרבן korban and was
under the sort of what and was sanctified, however it was sanctified,
it should in the end end up as a קרבן. korban. So
therefore when you sell it, although the proceeds are going to the
treasury and were sanctified for the treasury, you want to make sure
that it eventually gets brought as a קרבן, korban, so you sell
it to people that have to bring a קרבן korban with the
understanding that they're going to use it for a קרבן. korban. Fine.
So that's an idea that we'd like to see it end up
as a קרבן. korban. The fundamental sanctity is to the Temple treasury.
You might also remember, however, that this is a חידוש. chiddush. A,
you just might think that his intention was that which גמרא Gemara
say if it could be used as a קרבן. korban. On the
other hand, if he's sanctifying all his property, it makes sense he
meant it in the same way and he does it for the
Temple treasury. But you might also remember right that there is a
there's an issue that it's forbidden to sanctify things that are unblemished
animals for the Temple treasury. Okay? So to say that even so
that's how we interpret it is of course a surprise. That's what
he says. That presumably is the תנא tanna of our משנה, Mishnah,
Rabbi Eliezer.
Isn't it also forbidden to give everything you have to the Temple
treasury?
Yeah, that might be true also. Okay. Yeah, but you mean not
more than a חומש. chomesh. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, Rabbi
Yehoshua says, no, even though for the rest of your property it
meant treasury, for the animals it means קרבן. korban. זכרים הן עצמן
יקרבו עולות, Zecharim hen atzman yikrevu olot,
the male animals that could be brought should be brought as an
עולה, olah, ונקבות ימכרו לצורכי שלמים ויביא בדמיהן עולות. unekevot yimachru letzorchei
shelamim veyavi bidmaihen olot.
The females have the קדושה kedushah of an עולה, olah, but you
can't bring them as an עולה olah because they are female. So
you sell them to people that need to bring a שלמים shelamim
so they'll eventually be brought as a קרבן, korban, but the money,
which means what their קדושה kedushah was, the money should be used
to bring an עולה. olah. So they have קדושה kedushah as a
שלמים. shelamim. Right. Why? Because since you said הקדש סתם, hekdesh stam,
not just הרי, harei, הקדש סתם, hekdesh stam, so in the context
of בדק הבית bedek habayit what it means is fully owned by
הקדש. hekdesh. So even when we interpret it as a קרבן, korban,
we're going to interpret it in a sense of הקדש hekdesh as
it's fully out of mine, out of mine and human control. What
type of a קרבן korban is like that? An עולה. olah. So
therefore we interpret it as an עולה. olah. If you can't bring
a female עולה, olah, so you sell it, you use the money
for that. You try to make sure it gets brought as a
שלמים shelamim as well. One second, and there was a debate if
you remember before, do you have to wait for it to have
a blemish? Or is the fact that it's female enough that it
cannot it's fundamentally be an עולה olah that that you can automatically
sell redeem it even without a blemish? That was my question. No,
your question. That was debated before. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to say the following. Here it does not sound like you need
a blemish. It just sounds like you sell it straight. Okay. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So anyway, our משנה Mishnah is
not
Rabbi Yehoshua. ושאר נכסים לבדק הבית, Ush'ar nechasim lebedek habayit, and everything
else goes to the treasury. Now, ופליגא דרב אדא בר אהבה. Upleiga
deRav Adda bar Ahava. This idea that Rabbi Eliezer says that even
when you sanctify animals it goes to the בדק הבית, bedek habayit,
this argues on Rav Adda bar Ahava. Because he says that even
Rabbi Eliezer would agree in times that when you sanctify animals it
goes as a קרבן. korban. Let's take a look. דאמר רב אדא
בר אהבה
אמר רב, De'amar Rav Adda bar Ahava amar Rav, בעדר שכולו זכרים,
be'eder shekullo zecharim, if all you had in your flock were were
male animals, then and you said I'm sanctifying them, so you could
translate it to mean as an עולה. olah. There'd be no logical
problem. You didn't have other things. You didn't have cars and VCRs
and you didn't have female animals. It all could simply mean עולה.
olah. עולה olah then even he would agree. אפילו רבי אליעזר מודה
דלא שביק איניש קדשי מזבח ומקדיש לבדק הבית. afillu rabbi eliezer modeh
de-lo shevik inish kodshei mizbeach u-makdish le-bedek ha-bayit. Even he would agree
that people don't abandon קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbeach and ומקדיש לבדק הבית.
u-makdish le-bedek ha-bayit. לא נחלקו אלא בעדר שיש בו מחצה זכרים ומחצה
נקבות. lo nechelku ella be-eder she-yesh bo mechtza zecharim u-mechtza nekevot.
I don't know if literally it means מחצה. mechtza. But anyway they
only debated if there's males and females. There, since he can't interpret
the entire meaning as עולה olah because the females can't actually be
עולה, olah, so if he can't interpret the entire thing that way,
he basically wants the words to have a consistent meaning. And the
only consistent meaning is everything for the treasury. But everything for a
עולה olah would not work because of the females.
ורבי יהושע? v'rabbi yehoshua?
Well, because they could, but again since you said הקדש, hekdesh, we're
assuming that it has to mean a הקדש hekdesh that you're totally
divesting yourself from. דרבי אליעזר סבר אין חולק את נדרו. de-rabbi eliezer
savar ein cholek et nidro. You do not split your vow. ומדנקבות
לאו עולות זכרים נמי לאו עולות. u-mide-nekevot lav olot zecharim nami lav
olot. Since the females can't be עולות, olot, even though they can
have קדושת עולה, kedushat olah, they can't themselves be an עולה, olah,
then since you obviously don't mean that, then you don't mean it
by the males and they all are going לבדק הבית. le-bedek ha-bayit.
ורבי יהושע סבר חולק את נדרו. v'rabbi yehoshua savar cholek et nidro.
No, you can split it, and it's not even such a splitting
for him because even the females are sanctified with קדושת עולה. kedushat
olah. That's one version of the debate. Okay, לשון אחר, lashon acher,
another version of the debate, אמרה, amrah, אמר רב אדא בר אבא
אמר רב, amar rav adda bar abba amar rav, בשלא הקדיש אלא
בהמה, be-she-lo hikdish ella behemah, when all you have, not when all
you have is males, he agrees. Even if all you have is
animals, he agrees, males and females. אפילו רבי אליעזר מודה דלא שביק
איניש קדשי מזבח ומקדיש לבדק הבית. afillu rabbi eliezer modeh de-lo shevik
inish kodshei mizbeach u-makdish le-bedek ha-bayit. That if it's all animals, you
meant for קרבן. korban. Fine, the females will קדושת עולה kedushat olah
and you'll redeem it, but ultimately it's all for קרבן korban if
it's all animals. He would agree in that case. לא נחלקו אלא
כשיש שאר נכסים עמהם. lo nechelku ella keshe-yesh shear nechasim imahem. The
only debate is that you had other things that clearly could not
be קרבנות. korbanot. You had your VCR. I know, DVD player.
רבי אליעזר סבר אין אדם חולק נדרו. rabbi eliezer savar ein adam
cholek nidro. Clearly there for the non-animals you meant קדשי בדק הבית.
kodshei bedek ha-bayit. And since you meant that by your DVD player,
you don't split the meaning, you meant one thing, and therefore everything
was for בדק הבית. bedek ha-bayit. מדישאר נכסים לא קדשי מזבח בהמה
נמי לא קדשי מזבח. mi-de-shear nechasim lo kodshei mizbeach behemah nami lo
kodshei mizbeach. Since the other things are not to the altar,
the animals also are not. ורבי יהושע סבר, v'rabbi yehoshua savar, and
Rabbi Yehoshua says, no, I am so much disposed to read that
you give things to the altar as a preference that I will
say that you meant different things. חולק את נדרו, cholek et nidro,
you split your vow. ודמיהן יפלו, u-dmeihen yippelu, so the females, it
should probably be זכרים zecharim are עולות olot and the females are
sold, ודמיהן יפלו משאר נכסים לבדק הבית. u-dmeihen yippelu mi-shear nechasim le-bedek
ha-bayit. I'm
sorry, ודמיהן יפלו משאר נכסים לבדק הבית. u-dmeihen yippelu mi-shear nechasim le-bedek
ha-bayit. Oh no, period. No, that's the next line. Okay, חולק את
נדרו, cholek et nidro, period. Okay, so now we have two versions.
That even though Rav Ashi says סתם הקדשות stam hekdeshot are לבדק
הבית, le-bedek ha-bayit, and that was Rabbi Eliezer, we're now saying it's
not so clear even Rabbi Eliezer would always say that. Maybe he
only says it when I'm forced to say that's what your statement
means because there are female animals, or certainly when I'm forced to
say that's what your statement means when there are non-animals there. But
maybe if all you had was animals or all you had was
male animals, maybe even he would say a סתם הקדש stam hekdesh
would be למזבח. le-mizbeach. So that's a question, would Rabbi Eliezer admit
in certain cases? Now we're just going to try to prove what
is the debate from the last line of the Mishnah. The last
line of the Mishnah said, ודמיהן יפלו משאר נכסים לבדק הבית. u-dmeihen
yippelu mi-shear nechasim le-bedek ha-bayit. That according to Rabbi Eliezer, when you
go ahead and sell the animals, the money goes with everything else
to the treasury. So it said everything else. So that makes it
clear that they were talking about a case where there was things
other than animals, right? Since you sell the animals, it goes with
everything else. בשלמא לשנא בתרא, bishlama lishna batra, according to the second
version, they debate when there are other things. היינו דתני עם שאר
נכסים לבדק הבית. haynu de-tani im shear nechasim le-bedek ha-bayit. That there,
that with the other stuff, right, they're debating with other things. That's
where he said you don't split your vow, but if there's only
animals,
he agrees to the מזבח. mizbeach. אלא לשנא קמא, ella lishna kama,
but according to the first version, that their whole debate was only
in a case when it was just animals. לתני יפלו לבדק הבית.
lisni yippelu le-bedek ha-bayit. Why did it just say go to the
treasury? Why did it say go with everything else to the treasury?
What everything else is there? It's only animals. So the Gemara says,
fine, תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, ודמיהן יפלו לבדק הבית. u-dmeihen
yippelu le-bedek ha-bayit. Fine, switch the text, that's what it says. Money
goes to the treasury, not with everything else. So now what do
you have? You have one opinion of Rabbi Yehoshua that says we
will always, even if we have to split your vow, we will
always interpret that you're giving things to the as
if possible to as a קרבן. korban. We have Rabbi Eliezer says
no, I'm prepared to say you're giving animals to בדק הבית. bedek
ha-bayit. In what case? So one version is in all cases. You
could have perfect male animals in front of you, which could be
used as an עולה, olah, and you say I'm מקדיש makdish it,
we would say it means לבדק הבית. le-bedek ha-bayit. That's an extreme
version of Rabbi Eliezer. Then you have more limited ones. No, no,
no, he agrees I would want to interpret it as a קרבן.
korban. Only when I'm not able to because part of it doesn't
mean it. What does it mean part of it doesn't mean it?
Either because part of it is female animals, so they can't be
themselves an עולה... olah... Or certainly if part of it is non-animals
as well. In that case, since part of the vow can't mean
a קרבן, Korban, the rest won't, but if it could mean a
קרבן, Korban, maybe even he would be prepared first to interpret it
as a קרבן Korban rather than as something else. Okay, we will
end here.